<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands sad estate &amp; condition lamented in this just complaint taken up against the greatest part of her inhabitants because of their great abominations and treacherous dealings, both with God and man, for which cause the terrible and righteous judgements of the Lord are coming upon them and the land : wherein is also contained some prophecies and exhortations / by George Fox, the Younger.</title>
            <author>Fox, George, d. 1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40336</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2000</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16843</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12861624</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12861624</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94684</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40336)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94684)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 380:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands sad estate &amp; condition lamented in this just complaint taken up against the greatest part of her inhabitants because of their great abominations and treacherous dealings, both with God and man, for which cause the terrible and righteous judgements of the Lord are coming upon them and the land : wherein is also contained some prophecies and exhortations / by George Fox, the Younger.</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, d. 1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94684:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ENGLANDS SAD Eſtate &amp; Condition LAMENTED, IN THIS JUST COMPLAINT, Taken up againſt the greateſt part of her <hi>Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants,</hi> Becauſe of their great <hi>Abominations,</hi> and <hi>Treacherous Dealings,</hi> both with <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man;</hi> For which Cauſe the <hi>Terrible</hi> and <hi>Righteous Judgements</hi> of the Lord are coming upon them, and the Land.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN Is alſo contained ſome PROPHECIES and EXHORTATIONS.</p>
            <p>By <hi>George Fox,</hi> the Younger.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi> at the <hi>Black-Spread-Eagle</hi> and <hi>Windmil</hi> in <hi>Martins le Grand,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:94684:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94684:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ENGLANDS</hi> Sad Eſtate and Condition, <hi>LAMENTED,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>OH ENGLAND, <hi>England!</hi> The <hi>Abominations</hi> of the greateſt part of thy <hi>Inhabitants,</hi> who can declare them! They have reached Heaven, ſo as they are come up before the Lord, the Jealous God; and <hi>Wo</hi> unto that part of thy <hi>Inhabitants,</hi> who have ſinned out the Day of their <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation,</hi> and have wholly ſlighted the Day of <hi>God's patience,</hi> and <hi>long Forbearance,</hi> and would have none of his <hi>Reproof,</hi> but have altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rejected the ſame, and have made a mock at <hi>Sin,</hi> and have ſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves with their own <hi>Deceivings</hi> and <hi>Luſts,</hi> and have gone a Whoring from under the God of their Lives: Wherefore thus ſaith the Lord, the onely God; <hi>I will make ſuch become a Hiſſing</hi> and <hi>Reproach, and my Anger they ſhall not be able to Eſcape, becauſe of their provoking Abominations,</hi> and <hi>Treacherous Dealings both with</hi> Me <hi>and</hi> Man.</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>England, England!</hi> How have, and yet do, a great part of <hi>thy Inhabitants</hi> Ruſh into <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and all manner of <hi>Profaneſs</hi> and grievous <hi>Abominations,</hi> even as the <hi>Horſe</hi> and <hi>Mighty</hi> Ruſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Battel! How do they drink in <hi>Iniquity</hi> even as the <hi>Ox,</hi> or <hi>Parched Ground,</hi> drinketh in Water! Oh! What manner of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation</hi> ſhall I make for thee, my <hi>Native Countrey!</hi> Or, What manner of <hi>Complaint</hi> may I take up againſt a great part of thine <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants,</hi> who have long Sought, and yet ſeek thy <hi>Ruine</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction!</hi> Verily, their Actions have Declared them to be like the Inhabitants of <hi>Sodom;</hi> Yea, their ſins have rendred them to be as bad as thoſe of <hi>Gomorrah.</hi> O they have <hi>Vexed</hi> the Righteous Soul; Yea, and they have <hi>Grieved</hi> the Spirit of the Lord from <hi>Day</hi> to <hi>Day</hi> with their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt Converſations.</hi> They have multiplied their <hi>Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions,</hi> and heaped up their <hi>Iniquities</hi> till they are become as the Sand on the Sea-ſhore without Number. Oh! The Lord hath long ſtriven with them; yea, He hath alſo long born their <hi>Iniquities,</hi> He would have gathered them to himſelf out of their <hi>Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations,</hi> Yea, he would oft have healed them, But they would not; but they have ſtiffned their Necks, and hardned their Hearts againſt the Lord and his Counſel day after day, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94684:3"/>have choſen their own <hi>wayes</hi> and <hi>works</hi> even to their <hi>own hurt,</hi> and would by no means be reclaimed; for when the Lord hath reproved them (by the Light of his Son in their own conſciences) and ſet their ſins in order before their eyes, they have <hi>ſtopped</hi> their <hi>Eares,</hi> and <hi>cloſed</hi> their <hi>Eyes,</hi> and willfully Rebelled againſt the Power of God, and trampled upon his Witneſs [the Light in them] as a thing of nought, counting it not worth the taking Notice of. And when the Lord hath raiſed up <hi>Prophets, Children,</hi> and <hi>Servants,</hi> and ſent them out, Commanding them <hi>to lift up their Voyces like Trumpets, to ſhew the People their Tranſgreſſions, and to preach Repentance and Amendment of Life:</hi> Yea, <hi>to warn and exhort them to turn from their Sins to God, and to lay before them their great Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and to Propheſie what ſhould come upon them, if they would not turn from the evil of their Doings.</hi> Oh! how have a great part of <hi>thy Inhabitants Scorned,</hi> and <hi>Derided</hi> theſe! Yea, how have many of <hi>thine Inhabitants Beaten, Whipt, Stock't, Stoned,</hi> and <hi>Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned</hi> ſome of theſe <hi>till Death,</hi> for bearing their Teſtimony for the Lord againſt <hi>a crooked</hi> and <hi>perverſe Generation,</hi> who <hi>hate</hi> ſuch as ſpeak <hi>uprightly,</hi> and <hi>abhor</hi> ſuch as <hi>reprove Sin</hi> in the Gate, that ſo it is even thus come to paſs in thee, <hi>O England, That he that departeth from Iniquity, maketh himſelf a Prey</hi> to this Generation of <hi>Evil doers,</hi> whoſe hearts are ſet upon their <hi>Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts, Idolatry,</hi> and <hi>grievous Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations!</hi> and the Lord hath beheld it, and it pleaſeth him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is <hi>no true Judgement:</hi> for theſe Evil doers are <hi>all</hi> gone out of the way; yea there is <hi>none</hi> of them that regard to do the thing that's <hi>Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t</hi> and <hi>Good,</hi> any further than it may be <hi>advantagious</hi> to their own <hi>Corrupt Deſignes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh <hi>England, England!</hi> How oft hath the Lord God ſmote <hi>thy Rulers</hi> and <hi>Mighty,</hi> and <hi>Proud Men!</hi> how oft hath he laid their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in the Duſt! Yea, How oft hath he <hi>Overturned</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded</hi> thy <hi>Mighty Men,</hi> even thy <hi>Men</hi> of <hi>War,</hi> with thy <hi>Princes, Nobles,</hi> and <hi>Captains</hi> of Thouſands, Hundreds, and Fifties! O how oft hath he <hi>Overturned thy Governments,</hi> and <hi>Changed thy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors!</hi> But how few of them have ſo <hi>Regarded</hi> the <hi>Out-goings</hi> of the Lord in all theſe things as they ought to have done? And how few of them have rightly <hi>Weighed</hi> and <hi>Conſidered</hi> the Cauſes for which the Lord hath brought or ſuffered ſo many <hi>Changes</hi> in the Land? Or, have thoſe who ſaw the Cauſes that provoked the Lord of Hoſts thus to Act, laboured ſo to remove them as they ought to do (or might)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94684:3"/>have done? Nay, Aſſuredly they have not; for the <hi>Luſts</hi> of this World, and the <hi>Pride</hi> of Life hath blinded the minds of moſt; and ſuch who have ſeen what their Duty was, the <hi>honour of this World,</hi> and that curſed <hi>Self-intere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t</hi> hath ſtopped and hindred moſt of them from doing thoſe things which they ſaw they ought (and which they had opportunity alſo) to have done. Oh! How have the <hi>new Governors</hi> in almoſt every <hi>Change</hi> of <hi>late,</hi> cryed out of the <hi>Tiranny</hi> and <hi>great Oppreſſion</hi> of thoſe whom they did Succeed? and, how have moſt of them <hi>Vowed</hi> unto God, <hi>Declared</hi> to, and <hi>Promiſed</hi> the People, <hi>That they would Remove the Burdens and Oppreſſions that the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Rulers had Laid, and Continued upon them:</hi> But <hi>alas!</hi> very few of them, have regarded <hi>their Vowes, Declarations, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,</hi> either <hi>to God</hi> or <hi>Man;</hi> but in <hi>Treachery</hi> and <hi>Deceit</hi> have they gone on, Serving themſelves and their own Luſts, and not the Lord nor their Generation faithfully: For, although many of them have been very <hi>large in Promiſes</hi> and <hi>Good Words</hi> (whereby they have long ſought to Deceive the hearts of the People) yet it is but very <hi>Little</hi> that hath been done for their <hi>true Liberty;</hi> becauſe that wicked Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which ſeeketh to make it ſelf great by the Ruine of others, hath <hi>Ruled,</hi> and doth yet <hi>Rule,</hi> in the hearts of many Rulers; and this is of the Devourer and Deſtroyer, who cannot <hi>forgive Enemies,</hi> but Crys out of <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Treaſon,</hi> labouring to exaſperate the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Others, that ſo occaſions may be gotten, if poſſible, againſt them, thereby to bring them under, and keep them in Bondage.</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>England, England!</hi> Such is thy ſad <hi>Eſtate</hi> and <hi>Condition,</hi> that ſeverall of thy <hi>Rulers</hi> are; and have been, as <hi>roaring Lyons,</hi> even greedy <hi>to Devoure;</hi> And many of thy <hi>Teachers</hi> have been, and yet are, like <hi>Troops of Robbers,</hi> Robbing and Spoiling of many of thine Inhabitants. Oh! How have moſt of thy <hi>Prie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts Temporized,</hi> and <hi>Daubed</hi> with every Power, as they have come up in the <hi>many Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges!</hi> How have they encreaſed <hi>Envy, Wars,</hi> and <hi>Deſtructions,</hi> amongſt thy <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>People!</hi> How have they <hi>one time Cryed up,</hi> and <hi>Prayed</hi> for the <hi>ſame Thing,</hi> which, at <hi>another time,</hi> they have <hi>Cryed down,</hi> and <hi>Prayed againſt!</hi> Oh! Who ſhall ever believe them? Their <hi>god</hi> is their <hi>Belly;</hi> and who is it that many of them would not Joyn unto, if thereby they might be upheld in <hi>Pride, Idleneſs,</hi> and <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</hi> How oft would they <hi>Change again and again?</hi> And what <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry</hi> is there that many of them would not Run into for their <hi>Bellies ſake?</hi> Ah poor Nation! Are they not yet ſtriving to kindle a Flame
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94684:4"/>within thy Bowels? Hath not the Lord divided them? and, are they not labouring with all their might to <hi>Divide</hi> and <hi>Rend</hi> thy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants yet <hi>more</hi> and <hi>more?</hi> Yea, ſurely, and it is Juſt with the Lord to ſuffer it to be ſo; becauſe of the greatneſs of their <hi>Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations,</hi> which are daily encreaſed.</p>
            <p>Ah poor Land! How art thou overſpread with <hi>Wasters</hi> and <hi>Spoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers!</hi> who like <hi>Caterpillars</hi> devour thy <hi>Pleaſant Fruit.</hi> Oh! the <hi>Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms</hi> and <hi>Idolatries,</hi> that are daily committed and acted in thee, Who can Declare them! Oh! thy <hi>Chief City,</hi> thy <hi>Chief City,</hi> that <hi>bloody City!</hi> Can its <hi>Abominations</hi> be <hi>Parallel'd</hi> in the Earth! Surely it hath Exceeded <hi>Sodom</hi> in Wickedneſs. The Lord is very <hi>Angry</hi> with a great part of its Inhabitants, and his <hi>Vengeance</hi> is nigh to come upon them. <hi>Wo unto you Whoremongers, Drunkards, Gluttons, Swearers, Curſers, Blaſphemers, Cheaters,</hi> and <hi>Idolaters! Wo unto you, Proud, Wanton,</hi> and <hi>Prophane, Vain Perſons! Wo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, Mountebanks, Stage-players, Bear-batters, Gamſters,</hi> and all manner of <hi>Abominable Workers,</hi> and you that Build up <hi>Towers, Scaffolds,</hi> and <hi>Vain Heatheniſh Repreſentations</hi> and <hi>ſuch like;</hi> and make and garniſh <hi>Images,</hi> to draw peoples minds after <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and for your <hi>Curſed Gain</hi> and <hi>Lusts,</hi> in pretence of <hi>Honouring your King.</hi> Oh! How are people drawn into <hi>Gazing</hi> and <hi>Wondring</hi> after theſe <hi>Abominations!</hi> It grieveth the Righteous Soul to behold ſuch great <hi>Wickedneſs!</hi> Oh! You <hi>Wicked</hi> and <hi>Abominable Workers,</hi> and <hi>Devourers</hi> of the Creation! The Lord God will meet with you in a time when ye are little aware of Him, He'l <hi>Stain your Pride, Vain Glory</hi> and <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and give you your Portion amongſt <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourers</hi> (except you ſpeedily Repent) and your <hi>Abetters, Strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> and <hi>Helpers forward</hi> of ſuch Ungodlineſs (that do it know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly) and <hi>Delighters</hi> therein, The Lord will not acquit you, He'l ſmite you for theſe things, and that right ſoon. O! Ye, <hi>Idolatrous people,</hi> Do you think, that the Lord God of Pitty and Patience, ſuffered your King to Hide himſelf from his Enemies <hi>in an Oake,</hi> for that end, that ye might <hi>Devour</hi> his Creatures in make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an <hi>Idol of it?</hi> Is this the uſe you make of that which you ſay was <hi>Gods Mercy</hi> towards you? Is not this the way to turn thoſe things, that might have been Mercies to you, into Plagues and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? Oh! How do you <hi>Daily provoke</hi> the Lord againſt <hi>Your ſelves,</hi> and your <hi>King?</hi> Oh! You <hi>Wicked Workers,</hi> How dare you make <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations</hi> of <hi>Deſtruction</hi> and <hi>Ruine?</hi> How dare you make a Sport
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94684:4"/>of ſuch things? Verily, <hi>your Provocations</hi> are great, wherewith <hi>you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke</hi> the <hi>Just God;</hi> And it will be Juſt with him to bring <hi>Ruine, Deſolation,</hi> and <hi>Deſtruction</hi> upon <hi>you</hi> and your <hi>City;</hi> Verily, great is the Judgement that is nigh you, and your ſins draw it on you apace. Do you think that the Lord caſt out <hi>Back-ſliders, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfaithful men,</hi> to ſet up and eſtabliſh <hi>Idolaters</hi> and open <hi>Prophane perſons?</hi> Nay ſurely: Therefore <hi>Tremble</hi> ye <hi>Wicked Workers,</hi> and <hi>Howl</hi> ye <hi>Prophane Idolaters,</hi> for the <hi>Mighty</hi> and <hi>Terrible day</hi> of the Lord <hi>is near</hi> to break out upon you. Thus ſaith the Lord God, I'le <hi>Scat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> I'le <hi>Scatter,</hi> I'le <hi>Split, Divide,</hi> and <hi>Separate:</hi> I'le <hi>Break</hi> and <hi>Daſh to Peices, and none ſhall be able to Gather, Bind up, or Joyn together: For mine Anger is kindled, and my Jealouſe ſhall burn till I have devoured mine Enemies,</hi> ſaith the Lord.</p>
            <p>Therefore ye people of <hi>England</hi> (that yet live in wickedneſs) who have not wholly finned out the day of your <hi>Viſitation,</hi> To you I now ſpeak; You that ſeel the Lord yet ſtriving with you; O <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, Return</hi> ſpeedily unto the Manifeſtation of his Spirit, whereby he ſtrives with you, to ſhew you your <hi>Abominations,</hi> and to draw and lead you out of the ſame; O be not ſtill <hi>Stiff-necked,</hi> but hearken to the Word of the Lord, which ſheweth you the thoughts and Intents of your Hearts, and hearken and be obedient to the Call thereof, that ſo by its power you may <hi>Hasten</hi> out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> both <hi>Young</hi> and <hi>Old, Rich</hi> and <hi>Poor, High</hi> and <hi>Low, Noble</hi> or <hi>Ignoble, Profeſſor</hi> or <hi>Profane,</hi> who yet are there; For the Lords Controverſie is great with <hi>Babylon</hi> her <hi>Merchants,</hi> and <hi>Inhabitants,</hi> and he will not much longer ſpare, but he will ſuddenly ſmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and none ſhall be able to hinder his ſtroak: Yea, yea he will <hi>wound</hi> and none ſhall be able <hi>to heal;</hi> For the <hi>meaſure</hi> of her <hi>Iniquities, Idolatries,</hi> and <hi>Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms</hi> are <hi>nigh full,</hi> and the Wine of her Fornications, hath cauſed the Fatts to overflow, and ſhe is come up into remembrance before the Lord the Juſt God, who will Plague her and all her <hi>Merchants</hi> and <hi>Inhabitants</hi> according to their <hi>Abominations,</hi> whereby they have grievouſly provoked <hi>Him.</hi> Therefore, come out of her, whilſt Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Time is offered, leſt you periſh with her in her Judgments, which the Lord is Strongly and Swiftly bringing upon her.</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>England, England!</hi> A day of <hi>Sorrow</hi> and <hi>Calamity</hi> is come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon many of thy <hi>Inhabitants,</hi> I have long been ſenſible of it; even a day of ſuch <hi>Breaking, Confuſion</hi> and <hi>Judgement,</hi> as hath
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94684:5"/>not been <hi>for a long ſpace;</hi> For thy People have Wearied out the Lord <hi>with their Iniquities,</hi> and grieved his holy Spirit <hi>with their Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations,</hi> days without number.</p>
            <p>On <hi>England, England!</hi> The Lord hath a <hi>Precious</hi> and <hi>Holy Seed</hi> in thee; Yea, He hath a <hi>Remnant;</hi> which he hath Raiſed by his Power to, &amp; for himſelf, which are exceeding precious in his ſight; and theſe a great part of thine Inhabitants have <hi>Shamefully entreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> and <hi>grievouſly oppreſſed,</hi> and <hi>perſecuted;</hi> And they have <hi>Patiently</hi> born the ſame, and have laboured in the Life of <hi>Innocency,</hi> and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of <hi>Emanuel,</hi> to Inform thy <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>People</hi> in the Things that are <hi>Juſt</hi> and <hi>True,</hi> and have ſhewn them the <hi>Wayes</hi> which have, and do <hi>Diſpleaſe</hi> the Lord, and have Exhorted and Warned thy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, Time after Time: But notwithſtanding their <hi>Doctrine, Lives,</hi> and <hi>Converſations</hi> have manifeſted their <hi>Innocency</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs</hi> of <hi>Hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> before God and Man, Yet have many of thy <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>People, Oppreſſed</hi> them <hi>more</hi> and <hi>more;</hi> Some <hi>Spoiling their Goods,</hi> others <hi>Impriſoning their Bodies,</hi> in filthy <hi>Holes</hi> and <hi>Dungeons,</hi> till Severall of them have Sealed their Teſtimony for the Lord with <hi>their Blood,</hi> which cryeth <hi>for Vengeance</hi> in the Ears of the Almighty, and the Lord hath heard the Cry thereof, and hath looked down and beheld the <hi>Actings</hi> of the ſons of men, and he is near to Viſit; Yea, the Lord hath <hi>beheld,</hi> and doth <hi>behold,</hi> the Snares that have been, and are laid for the Innocent, who have no other Helper but him alone; and therefore they have Committed their Cauſe unto Him who ſhall bring it to paſs: Yea, he hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Notice, how ſeveral of thy <hi>Rulers</hi> have combin'd together, and endeavoured <hi>to Force</hi> His <hi>Babes</hi> to Violate his Royal Law, and to Break his Command (who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all</hi>) to Uphold and Obey theirs, which is Contrary to his; Yea, He hath taken Notice of the <hi>Cruel Sufferings;</hi> and great <hi>Temptations</hi> of his People, who, many of them, are <hi>yet Impriſoned;</hi> and both their <hi>Bodies</hi> and <hi>Eſtates</hi> threatned to be Deſtroyed (by ſome evil men) if they will not break the Royal Law and Commandement of Chriſt, which he hath placed in their hearts to Obey &amp; Do. Oh! The Lord hath ſeen the <hi>Partiality</hi> and <hi>evil Intents</hi> of ſeveral of the <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Rulers</hi> of this Land, who have had Power to let the Innocent go free, and yet keep many of his <hi>Miniſters</hi> and <hi>Servants</hi> (many of which have outward Eſtates) Priſoners in many places; although they have no more againſt them, than againſt thoſe whom they have turned
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94684:5"/>forth, which is nothing elſe but for their Obeying the Command of Chriſt in them, (who this day ſaith unto his People, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> as he ſaid to his Diſciples formerly) and for <hi>meeting together,</hi> and <hi>Speaking</hi> and <hi>Praying</hi> in his Name, for the <hi>Edifying, Comforting</hi> and <hi>Building up one another in their moſt holy Faith.</hi> The Lord hath alſo taken notice, that when ſome of the Rulers might Relieve <hi>the Innocent,</hi> and let <hi>the Oppreſſed go free,</hi> they will not; and then to cover themſelves, they will ſay, <hi>They cannot act contrary to the Law:</hi> But when a Ruler will act that which he hath no Law for; he can then plead <hi>a Prerogateve Royal for that:</hi> and thus are the innocent Lambs of Chriſt made a Prey upon.</p>
            <p>Oh! the <hi>Oppreſsions</hi> of his People, and others, are great this day in thee, O Land; and the Crying of the <hi>Fatherleſs,</hi> the <hi>Widows</hi> and the <hi>Needy</hi> is come up before the Lord God of Compaſſion, who will thorowly plead the Cauſe of his People, and the Poor and Needy of the Land.</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>England, England!</hi> I have oft heard and treaſured up what the Lord hath ſaid in me, concerning thy Inhabitants; but now muſt I declare it in the Appointed Seaſon, Thus hath the Lord ſpoken in me for a long time, concerning thy Inhabitants, ſaying, <hi>The People are <hi>too many,</hi> the People are <hi>too many;</hi> I will <hi>thin them,</hi> I will <hi>thin them:</hi>
               </hi> [Mark] that is, <hi>He will make them <hi>fewer,</hi>
               </hi> for they cumber the Ground. And the Spirit of the Lord hath oft ſignified unto me, for a long time, <hi>That an <hi>Over-flowing Scourge,</hi>
               </hi> yea, <hi>even an exceeding <hi>great</hi> and <hi>terrible Iudgement</hi> is to come upon thee, O Land!</hi> and that many in thee <hi>ſhall fall</hi> and be <hi>taken away</hi> in the Judgement; and the Spirit of the Lord ſignifieth unto me, that the <hi>time draweth nigh,</hi> and that the <hi>Decree</hi> of the Lord is ſo firm, that though ſome of the Lords Children and Prophets could appear ſo, as to ſtand in the <hi>Gap,</hi> yet ſhould not that alter his Decree, only in the Righteouſneſs of the Lamb they ſhall be hid and ſaved from his Wrath, what ever may be done to any of their Bodies; but his fierce Wrath and Indignation ſhall be poured forth upon the Ungodly, and a <hi>great Deſolation</hi> and <hi>Deſtruction</hi> ſhall there be; for he will <hi>overturn</hi> and <hi>overturn,</hi> till he hath <hi>diſ-throned</hi> &amp; <hi>thrown down</hi> the <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> and <hi>exalted</hi> &amp; <hi>eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> the Kingdom of his <hi>Dear Son,</hi> over all the Kingdoms of the World; and the <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Dominion,</hi> and the Greatneſs of the Kingdom under the whole Heaven ſhall be given to the Holy People, the Saints of the Moſt High, <hi>whoſe Kingdom is an Everlaſting Kingdom,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:94684:6"/>and all Dominions ſhall ſerve and obey him, who is King of Saints.</p>
            <p>Behold, ye <hi>Deſpiſers,</hi> and <hi>Wonder!</hi> This is the Work which the Lord will accompliſh by his own Power, though you will in no wiſe believe it; but you ſhall feel, even both <hi>Hypocrites</hi> and <hi>Prophane,</hi> that the Lord is able to bring to paſs the thing that is in his heart.</p>
            <p>And you who now think <hi>to ſet up</hi> and <hi>eſtabliſh</hi> your <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and to live in <hi>Pzophaneſs</hi> without <hi>control;</hi> and you who appear <hi>ſo hot</hi> againſt ſome of theſe things, and labour to ſtop and pull them down (mark) that you might ſet up and eſtabliſh your own <hi>Hypocritical Will-worſhip</hi> in another <hi>dark dead Form, I will fruſtrate <hi>you both,</hi>
               </hi> ſaith the Lord God, and <hi>you ſhall grind and waſte <hi>one</hi> againſt <hi>another,</hi> as the</hi> upper <hi>and</hi> nether <hi>Milſtone; And I will pluck out from you, and preſerve a holy Seed, beyond expectation;</hi> and I will <hi>be avenged on you</hi> for that which you have already <hi>bruiſed,</hi> or ſhall yet <hi>bruiſe</hi> [mark] And I will <hi>hurry</hi> and <hi>hurl <hi>you round</hi>
               </hi> with a mighty <hi>Stream;</hi> for the Waters ſhall <hi>roar</hi> and <hi>ſwell:</hi> And after I have executed <hi>my venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> upon the <hi>Rebellious</hi> and <hi>Treacherous Dealers,</hi> I will then bring forth the <hi>Remnant</hi> of my Holy Seed, which ſhall be <hi>preſerved</hi> from their <hi>Fury,</hi> and they ſhall ſpread over all, in my Life, Power Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Wiſdom, wherein they ſhall ſtand in Dominion; Yea, and they ſhall rule the Earth in <hi>Mercy, Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>true Judgement;</hi> and they ſhall <hi>forgive</hi> and <hi>love their Enemies</hi> (as they do at this day) and do the thing that is <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>good</hi> unto all, without <hi>reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons;</hi> yea, they ſhall ſeek the good of the whole Creation in the <hi>true love</hi> and <hi>ſelf-denial;</hi> for the Spirit of <hi>Love, Meekneſs, Healing</hi> and <hi>Reſtoring</hi> ſhall mightily fill their tender Bowels, and my Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings ſhall fill their Dwelling place, and the Earth, for their ſaltes: theſe things will I accompliſh by my own Power, and in my own time, ſaith the Lord God.</p>
            <p>But although theſe things, touching the holy Remnant, ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be fulfilled in their Seaſon, Yet before they be fully accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, great will be the Tryals of many of the Righteous, and there will be <hi>great Judgements</hi> executed in thee, O land, by Him who oft-times maketh <hi>a fruitful Land barren,</hi> becauſe of the <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> of them that dwell therein; and Juſt will it be with Him to deal ſo with thee, becauſe of the <hi>great wickedneſs</hi> of the greateſt part of thy Inhabitants, who are departed and ſeparated from the Spirit of Mercy, Love, Compaſſion and Healing, and are labouring to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94684:6"/>
               <hi>Devour, Oppreſs,</hi> and <hi>Deſtroy</hi> one another, and the whole Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>England, England!</hi> There is alſo a People in thee who are come to ſee <hi>the Great <hi>Idolatry</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Superſtition,</hi> which many are now ſtriving to revive and <hi>ſet up</hi> in thee; yea, there is a People in thee, which ſee and believe that the Worſhip which is now a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up, with the <hi>Vain <hi>Muſick, Altars, Maſſe</hi>
               </hi> in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and the fooliſh needleſs <hi>
                  <hi>Garments</hi> of the <hi>Prieſts,</hi>
               </hi> and ſuch like <hi>Popiſh ſtuff,</hi> that theſe things are <hi>Idolatry, Folly</hi> and <hi>Vanity <hi>and butia mocking of God;</hi>
               </hi> and yet ſome of theſe People will run after this <hi>Vain Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> for <hi>ſelf-ends, ſtaviſh-fear,</hi> and to keep themſelves in eſteem with, or amongſt thoſe who plead for it: And others there are in thee; who inſtead of being ſorrowful for ſuch Abomination and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, or reproving the Practicers thereof in the ſolid, ſeaſoned, ſavoury Life and holy Dread of the Lord God, they write and ſpeak <hi>ſcoffingly</hi> of thoſe things, even to the ſtirring up one of another into <hi>vain Laughter,</hi> and ſo make a Sport of others <hi>Idolatry;</hi> and this grieveth the Spirit of the Lord alſo, and doth not convince, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperate and harden thoſe that are zealous for their <hi>blind Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Superſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are alſo a great number of <hi>brittle, fiery, raſh, unſatisfied people</hi> in thee, O Land, who are as <hi>unſtable</hi> as Water, and theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belling againſt the Light, not knowing the way of it, becauſe they abide not in the path thereof, they are <hi>reſtleſs, rouling,</hi> and <hi>raging</hi> oft-times like the Sea; One time they will have a <hi>Parliament,</hi> and cry out, <hi>They ſhall govern</hi> and <hi>heal them;</hi> and when they have gotten them, in a ſhort-time they grow weary of them: And then another time, they will cry out <hi>for a King,</hi> and ſay, <hi>He ſhall heal them,</hi> and <hi>make up their Breaches:</hi> But there people are not long of one mind, for they are much like the <hi>Athenians,</hi> who ſpent their time in little elſe but either <hi>to tell</hi> or <hi>to hear of ſome New thing:</hi> Theſe People alſo are like mighty Tydes in thy Chanels, <hi>O England,</hi> which one while run with <hi>Violence,</hi> driving all <hi>unſetled, light, unfixed</hi> things <hi>one way,</hi> and ſhortly after run with as much violence the contrary way: Therefore in a miſerable condition are thoſe Rulers whoſe ſtrength is in ſuch a People! And until Rulers come to be ſetled, and fixed in Him who is the <hi>Rock of Ages,</hi> and ſingly to rule in, and for Him, whom the Winds and the Seas obey, who maketh the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to ſtand on heaps, and divideth them hither and thither; and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94684:7"/>altereth the natural courſe of <hi>Tydes</hi> as he pleaſeth (as he hath done thine of late, to ſhew thee the Figure of the People) they can never be ſafe, neither will the People be ſtill'd long together; but there will be <hi>Swellings, Ragings, Overflowings, ſore Breakings and Ruines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh! that the <hi>foregoing Rulers</hi> would have been perſwaded to have Received Him for their Teacher, who Ruleth in the Kingdoms of Men, then ſhould they not onely have ſeen, what the Lord caſt out others before them for, but they ſhould have been taught how to have denied all thoſe things which the Lord was angry with others for, and they ſhould have received Power to have abſtained from the ſame; but they would not hear and obey the Lord, nor his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and therefore were they caſt out alſo.</p>
            <p>And therefore, Oh! that the <hi>Rulers</hi> that now are, would be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded (whilſt they have their Day) by the Lord and his Servants, to receive the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> to be their <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Teacher,</hi> and then they ſhould not onely ſee for <hi>what cauſe</hi> the Lord caſt them out, and <hi>others</hi> in their Age, but they ſhould be taught to <hi>deny</hi> and <hi>forſake</hi> all thoſe <hi>things</hi> which God was angry with them, and others for, and they ſhould receive Power to do thoſe things, which they and others before them left undone; But alas! How few are there that will <hi>Hear, Regard,</hi> and <hi>Obey</hi> the Prince of Life and his Followers, and therefore is Deſolation coming as a mighty Flood, which none ſhall be able to ſtop.</p>
            <p>Now all People, in what Sect or Opinion ſoever, in whom there are any true <hi>Breathings</hi> and <hi>Deſires</hi> after the Lord, and the way of his Holineſs, <hi>Fear not,</hi> neither <hi>be Diſmaid,</hi> becauſe of the <hi>Rage</hi> that you may yet ſee the Waters of the Land in, and becauſe of the <hi>Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>Cruelty</hi> of the People; But <hi>ſtand ſtill</hi> in that Life which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth <hi>Breathings</hi> and <hi>Thirſtings <hi>in you</hi>
               </hi> after the Lord, that you may come to ſee and feel his <hi>Salvation,</hi> and that you may be gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into that <hi>Patience, Meekneſs, Contentedneſs, Reſt, Peace,</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> which many of the dear Lambs and Children of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are gathered into, wherein they Lye down, and none can make them afraid, though their Bodies and Eſtates be oppreſſed and abuſed. Oh! <hi>Stick not, Stick not</hi> in your <hi>Forms</hi> without <hi>Power,</hi> neither Flee the Croſs, any longer; but wait in the True <hi>Simplicity,</hi> to feel God's hand of Tender Love, which he reacheth forth to, and manifeſteth <hi>in you,</hi> to lead and guide your minds into his Pure Worſhip, which is in the Spirit and in the Truth. Oh People! This
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94684:7"/>is the Worſhip that he will ſet up. He will be <hi>LORD</hi> and <hi>LAW<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GIVER</hi> in the Conſciences of his People; and thoſe that will not be content that <hi>EMMANUEL</hi> ſhould <hi>Reign</hi> over them, he will Slay them with the <hi>Sword</hi> of the <hi>Spirit, <hi>The Words of his Mouth.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh! <hi>Hearken, hearken</hi> a little, and <hi>ſtand ſtill,</hi> that you may bear the voice of the True Shepherd <hi>in your own Hearts,</hi> who calleth for Truth in the Inward Parts, and he will diſcover what lodgeth <hi>Within,</hi> and He will ſhew you the Way wherein you ſhould walk, and he will let you ſee what the Croſs is unto, and He will teach you when you are alone in your Beds, or where-ever you are; if you will receive Him who giveth you Life and Breath, whoſe <hi>gentle Reproofs</hi> and <hi>Inſtructions</hi> are the Way of Life.</p>
            <p>Therefore you in whom the <hi>Breathings</hi> and <hi>Deſires</hi> after the Lord are; Conſult not with <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> neither reaſon againſt the <hi>Croſs,</hi> but ſubmit to every Appearance of Gods Power in you, which appeareth to Crucifie the Fleſhly Birth and Nature; which hath ſtood, and doth ſtand in Rebellion and Enmity againſt the Pure and Precious Life, and Requirings of the Lamb of God; that ſo that Mind which is at enmity againſt God, and that Nature in <hi>you,</hi> which is diſobedient to his Commands in Spirit, may come to be Crucified, that ſo there may be a Change Inwardly felt and witneſſed, by the working of the mighty Power of Chriſt in your Inward Parts; and then the <hi>Deſires</hi> and <hi>Breathings</hi> which are Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten <hi>in you</hi> after <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> they will be ſtrengthened, and the <hi>Teachings</hi> of the Almighty will be Truly known, and you believing in the Power, you will receive Power to obey and Practiſe whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Lord ſhall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> make known unto you by his Spirit to be his Will and Requirings.</p>
            <p>Oh People! Let the <hi>Dread</hi> of the Lord <hi>Seize upon your Spirits,</hi> in this the Day of his Power, wherein he is <hi>Trying, Sifting</hi> and <hi>Winnow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the Nations, and wait to feel that Life ariſe <hi>within you,</hi> which beareth <hi>Teſtimony</hi> againſt <hi>all evil <hi>within</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>without;</hi> that ſo ye may become more and more acquainted with the <hi>Teachings, Draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> and <hi>Leadings thereof,</hi> that thereby you may be drawn and led out of thoſe things which have kept your Souls in the Death, and hindred you from enjoying the Pure Peace of God. And this know and conſider; that all that come to witneſs their Souls raiſed out of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94684:8"/>Death, and brought to enjoy the Peace of God, they muſt Believe in the Life of the Quickning Spirit, <hi>which is the Second Adam, the Lord from Heaven,</hi> who <hi>for Sin</hi> Condemneth <hi>Sin in the Fleſh,</hi> and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in the <hi>Inward Parts</hi> of man, to work <hi>out Sin</hi> and <hi>tranſgreſſion,</hi> (which hath Separated from God) and ſo to make clean the heart and inſide of male and female.</p>
            <p>Oh People! This is the Work of Chriſt the Son of God, even <hi>to make <hi>manifeſt</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>deſtroy</hi> the <hi>Works of the Devil,</hi> and ſo to reconcile man unto God, by the Virtue of his <hi>own Life,</hi> which he gave <hi>a Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome</hi> for many; and bleſſed are all thoſe that believe in the Life of the Son of God, and feel and know it <hi>manifeſted <hi>in their mortal fleſh:</hi>
               </hi> for they ſhall witneſs the Power of it to make all things new, and ſo their Souls will come up in the hand of God, and his Peace will be Received and Enjoyed.</p>
            <p>Oh people! <hi>Wait</hi> to know, and feel this Work of Chriſt <hi>within you,</hi> that ſo you may be made able to Stand in the Judgement, and to Endure the Tryal, and that you may be Hid from the Wrath of the Lamb, which is night to come upon the <hi>Rebellious.</hi> Oh! Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this, Thoſe that are his Followers, they come throw <hi>many Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations,</hi> and their <hi>overcoming</hi> their Enemies is <hi>by his Blood,</hi> not by <hi>a talk of it,</hi> but by <hi>the Virtue</hi> and <hi>Power of it</hi> ſprinkled <hi>in their Hearts,</hi> which waſheth and maketh them White, Clean, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Fault before God. Oh People my <hi>Bowels yearn!</hi> my <hi>Bowels yearn</hi> towards you! whoſe <hi>Deſires</hi> in any meaſure, are after the Lord: O that you would now Return with all your hearts unto Him, and obey the Voice of his Power <hi>in you;</hi> then ſhould you be made able to ſtand, and endure the fiery Trial which is come and coming. Oh! the Day <hi>haſtens</hi> wherein all <hi>Profeſſion</hi> that is not grounded in the Life and Power of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the ſhew of it be) it will be ſo ſhaken, that an utter Blaſting and withering ſhall come upon it; and for that cauſe the Lord doth, and will yet ſuffer great Trials to come, both upon the <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> and <hi>Poſſeſſors</hi> of his Name; that ſo his <hi>Children</hi> [the <hi>Poſſeſſors</hi>] may be manifeſted unto all, and diſcerned from all that are but <hi>Profeſſors,</hi> though never ſo fair and ſeemingly Covered; For all Coverings but what is of the Power and Spirit it ſelf, ſhall be too Narrow; and all that are not Covered with the Spirit and Power of <hi>Emma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel,</hi> their Shame and Nakedneſs ſhall appear more and more. This is the Teſtimony which the Spirit and Word of Truth giveth; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94684:8"/>
               <hi>He that hath an ear to hear, let him hear,</hi> before the day of his Viſitation be wholly paſt, and the things belonging to his Peace be hid from his Eyes: For <hi>yet a little while and the Voice ſhall be, <hi>He that is filthy, let him be filthy ſtill;</hi> For the Spirit of the Lord ſhall not always ſtrive with Fleſh,</hi> but his <hi>Plagues</hi> and <hi>Indignation</hi> ſhall be poured out upon ſuch as will not be <hi>gathered</hi> in the Day of his <hi>Patience, long Forbearance,</hi> and <hi>Free-Love;</hi> and He or She that Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth <hi>Father, Mother, Husband, Wife, Children, Houſe,</hi> or <hi>Land, Liberty, Honour,</hi> or <hi>any Thing</hi> more than <hi>the Life</hi> of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> ſhall be counted not worthy of him, and plainly manifeſted ſo to be: <hi>Read this who can; and he that can receive it, let him: For the Time draweth nigh that theſe Sayings muſt be fullfilled.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Printed <date>the 13. of the Second Moneth.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
